hello greetings
it's
November 11th 2022 we're in cohort one
of the textbook group
and we're coming back to chapter 10.
looking at the sections of 10
asking any questions about 10
thinking about any overview points
before next week
when it will be our final meeting
and we'll talk about feedback
fill out the form in future textbook
groups talk about project ideas next
steps talk about our plans for 2023 and
so on
um
but where do we
begin with 10.
we covered many of the sections once
last week
there's a lot of sections
the chapter kind of is like a
symphonic presentation
it has multiple
movements
and subsections
that have their own like Rhythm and
structure
let's go to the end
I think this is um
really important note
about learning and active engagements
which is if you're not
even before skin in the game and
psychological ownership and so on
if one is not
making
predictions
not just about material like what's
going to happen next in the TV show that
I'm watching
oh it surprised me
but about the consequences of one's
actions in the world
they will not be able to update those
models of action in the world
so you could be surprised and end up
being a good infer
in a passive inference setting
however doing
is what actually allows you
to learn in a totally different way
because
whether you realize it at the beginning
of the journey or not or whether you
even agree with this or not
those actions that you take
are chosen and exist on a trade-off
Frontier
of epistemic and pragmatic value
and so simply choosing to act
is a strategy
that opens up a space
for pragmatic as well as epistemic
action
it's kind of like the hyper prior on
active inference is how active
and one other
um no just that anyone can add anything
um this was a discussion with um with JF
and Camden
um
some days ago in in our research meeting
about the scaling debate in machine
learning all you need is scaling bigger
natural language models and so on
um and like how can active inference and
how can we
contextualize that and
improve the state of things and
um we talked about how importantly
GPT
does not choose its own inputs
and so yes it can engage within a
perception action Loop related to
receiving inputs and sending outputs
however in terms of its own training and
development
it's importantly
constraints
that's not necessarily A Bad Thing
it's just that
to actively select
what to what stimuli to sample
is very Central to active inference
from the ocular motor to the tactile
and
so
all of the Big Data training algorithms
do not select their own inputs
and then if they were to it could be
done in two ways it could be done in an
ad hoc way or principled way the ad hoc
way would be
um you do some kind of
um different architecture of a model
that you know predicts what inputs would
be valuable to train
or
you could think of a unified imperative
that would decide on both action and
learning rules Eric and Brock
yeah I suppose you could say that
reinforcement learning the the machine
is selecting its own
um
samples to get feedback on
now reinforcement learning is not gpd3
it's not language learning language
model learning but
um I think an earlier Paradigm maybe I
don't know I think they still use
reinforcement learning in deep learning
models although
um you know it was also I think a lot of
people are discouraged by that because
it's
it it you know as they say it's uh it's
a very narrow uh very weak low bandwidth
signal you're getting back
but it is an example of learning models
using generating their own samples
thanks Brock
um
I was gonna
I guess uh take tools biological place
we left off in last session of cicading
of like
being a kind of data cleaning process
almost or
um
stabilizing the you know the
like data set coming in and um that we
do have some
very very crude like uh you know
built-in labels for edges kind of in our
visual cortex right
uh that are
presumably evolutionary
um
and some decent evidence that
like maybe one level higher something
gestalt-like of like
edges and Heights you know
um
or uh
yeah just other certain kinds of like
really really uh generalized
[Music]
um
images or views that you might take that
have like very pronounced uh
definition edges of like like a
a prayer you know like a landscape of
you know our natural evolutionary
landscape being like somewhat comforting
or pleasing or something like this right
and walking over like a baby like eight
months or whatever crawling over a glass
but it looks like looks like they're
gonna fall and they're they react to
that right
um like these sort of things uh where
there's some sort of baked in like
priors or again like labeling right
um
there's no I mean are those hyper
parameters you know there's but then
they're not controlling their hyper
parameters
doing these models like so
um
yeah I mean
there's no affordance there for that
sort of like goal directed or selecting
data sets in any possible way or any of
that
so
I'm thinking of a of a British English
reading
of how the world should be
like
we talk about expectations and
preferences
and if someone says
like I should think so
it's not actually a normative
stance
it's like saying I I expect and prefer
myself I should be there at eight
whereas often should is interpreted as
purely normative
like I wish that you did this
[Music]
um
but should
actually does kind of condense that
expectation preference
um scenario and then to kind of come
back to the
um inherited World models
so yeah
um sequential processing steps can be
understood of
within a hierarchical processing
framework
where higher levels
have the interpretation as being hyper
parameters on lower levels
and I think we saw a little bit at the
end of um nine
which is basically for any and this also
speaks to the composability of Bayes
graphs
which is that you can always
have a variable as fixed
or you can have a hyper prior on that
and an uncertainty on the hyper prior or
you could wrap it in another base graph
but all of these can fall under the
category of how things should be for
that agents
and a business that thinks that there
should be
um a lot of Interest next year and is
wrong goes out of business
the organism that thinks that it should
be warm tomorrow night and doesn't plan
for the cold dies
and so the the should almost reflects
the whole cognitive stock
and the action selection
that makes it that way
one area that yeah I'll leave please
uh yeah I was reading the other day
about uh the importance of uh the
statistical regularity of uh any
particular environment and uh the way it
constrains uh The evolutionary
developments uh I mean uh for instance
for terrestrial animals uh the majority
of the objects are solid objects and of
course that's not the case for sea
animals but
um uh this I was wondering that uh when
an organism generates it or constructs
it its generative model uh how exactly
especially in the case of visual
perception uh how exactly these kind of
statistical regularities uh or let's say
uh the statistical regularities as
applied to their visual perception uh
translates into their generative models
because uh for the most part at least in
this textbook what we saw in generative
model is just exactly it is just
an abstract
conception of generative model and as
you say how the how the world should be
but I don't see how these kind of
um evolutionary
constraints or statistical regularities
of the environment
takes place
when a generative model is constructed
at each for each specific task because
in my view that would make a lot of
difference in constructing the other
priors according to those regularities
I'm not sure if I express my question
clearly enough but
yeah I was wondering how that's done in
active inference framework
yeah good question
um just on the visual note and then the
generative model on the visual note
there are some statistical regularities
of natural visual scenes
like
Pebbles on the ground trees and like
there's some autocorrelation functions
and some spectral density analyzes and
some fractal similarity things that
people have done so that like for quote
natural scenes
so not necessarily a skyscraper but
again like
the bodies of animals and um
natural settings with trees and plants
there are some like hyper parameters
that make the scene natural
which is interesting to think about in
these like image generating algorithms
and then
um to the second point about the
generative model
um it reminds me of jf's approach
towards Society of Minds
where it's like
spinning up generative models
now in that case it's symbolic logical
generative models but also we could
imagine Society of
statistical generative generative models
um
Eric
yeah I would just um Echo Ali's
question about how
um or you know a a a a a a a a gap in
you know what we've we've learned about
active inference which is how do these
models get made in the first place
um you know for the examples in the book
um well he walked in with the teammates
and a model for how team maze works and
that was probably
the most sophisticated
active inference model presented
um but when you get to
you know real world scenarios well
how are models of the world learned and
that's a big open question and you know
are they even what sense are they
generative models uh often predictive I
think but um
um you know are they probabilistic
generative models in the sense that we
think of them mathematically I I that's
you know somehow people model it that
way some people don't don't think so
um you know certainly neural networks
are discriminative or in many cases
um
so I just I guess agree that that's all
there's a lot of a lot of uh work unsaid
to be down there are a lot of questions
open
hmm
I wonder if some people hope for
perceptual control theory
to kind of Save the Day
which is like
we don't need to make a generative
models for the bewildering possibilities
of external States
but it might be enough
first to have bodies that can engage in
interception and homeostasis and
allostasis
and then
with that Machinery as as enabling
maybe all you need to know about the
external world is like it's good or it's
bad
and just like run away from bad things
and go towards good things
and then you have to you know you can
update your a matrix on whether you
think good or bad States emit
this or that kind of observation
but
[Music]
um
the the blanket
facilitates
the organism's hyper focus on its own
States
and might allow it to engage Less in
this open-ended structure model fitting
of the world
not that you wouldn't do better with
infinite resources in a better causal
model of the world
Brock
um let's open the kind of
discussed with JF actually too about um
some of his generative models are going
to be static and specified just like the
robot is literally
specified by him
um
it seems like if you wanted to you know
have a more General explanation or
process or whatever to get to whatever
human level or something
things that start exhibiting
those sort of behaviors or or
uh you know come insert with active
inference type models of like you would
need Devolution like like you would need
to evolve the system to that point
and then
you could ask a question like if you did
that
would you gain anything
compared to
just build Optimus and it's not as good
but it's a good like first order
approximation first step
of like towards something that would be
constrained in such a way that it's more
likely
to produce generative models that are
useful and
whatever could be human-like or whatever
you know
um
yeah conscious intelligent something
whatever
um but
I didn't see how yeah I mean any
possible explanations on the table for
like
how you get to something that's
whatever
ha that has some sort of central nervous
system you know or or conscious or
anything like that
um
did would all depend on something like
evolution
and and then that process is just
necessarily like very long and laborious
and if you're just if you're looking for
something novel then maybe you have to
do that but if you're just trying to get
the first order approximations something
similar to what already exists and why
go through all that you know it's
probably easier to just assume some
priors which is what JF is doing
so
this reminds me of the problem in
machine learning of one shot learning
where like a single image is shown and
the goal is to learn cat as a category
from one picture of a cat now
there are algorithms that do better or
worse but there's also some fundamental
limits of any type of One-Shot learning
like
to say nothing of over generalizing you
know overfitting but of course
so it's almost like this is um
statistics
slowly
retreating or advancing into biology
because it's like well
if if we don't want to do just one shot
learning on one data point or one data
set which is one datum still it's one
big datum
we want to have learning
model
okay now we want to have a learning
model with active selection of inputs
now we want to have
generators and basically like Landscapes
of models portfolios of models Bayesian
model reduction and structure learning
in the Bayesian setting
as being across distributions of models
and then that's where Evolution gets us
which is
populations of models existing in
different niches
and maybe if our data set is our
generative process
like maybe there are some models that
are doing like really well in this part
of the data set and there's other models
that are doing really well another part
of the data set
you don't just compromise them
or um you know ligate them together
their embodiments reflects the
statistical regularities of the
environment and I added this
um citation this is from Professor
Gordon my PhD advisor
and
it's like and there were several
subsequent papers that continued on this
theme but
it was like trying to get without
putting words in your mouth or anything
like that like
trying to make this point that you
couldn't you can't just look at the
collective Behavior or the end of you
know everything's Collective all the way
down so you can't just look at the
behavior of an ants
and just say like whether it's like good
or bad or fit or not because there's
Landscapes with uniform and passy
distributions
which is exactly the case for
statistical distributions
there's cases where the cost of stopping
is high or low relative to the cost of
operating
and then there's situations where
basically interruptions can be
easily recreated or not
among others
um
and it just like
degenerative process is what the
generative model is fit too
so it's an incomplete sentence or an
incomplete expression
to be like
speculating on just generative model
architectures
without a little bit of at least an
acknowledgment of the statistical
regularities of the generative process
the generative process is a metronome
that's alternating between states
then your generative model
you have some suggestions for how to
design it
if the generative process is another
agent like you
then that's another that's like the
generative adversarial neural network
case or the game theory case or the
theory of Mind case or the
communications case like
those are different settings
um
returning to chapter six
what are we
modeling
what is the appropriate form for the
generative model how to set it up and
then how to set up the generative
process and I think we even discussed a
little bit then
like
this is kind of a generative model first
approach
whereas one could imagine step four
moving to step
one and a half
or you know
however but but
um it doesn't make sense you know
nothing in biology makes sense except in
the lay of evolution famous dubjansky
quote
so
will we have similar memes you know
nothing about the generative model is
going to make sense except in light of a
generative process
the state transitions in the generative
model
they are parameterized given the weight
of the leg
that's not part of the parameterization
of the state space
but in fact that parameterization makes
sense in light of gravity friction
[Music]
the solidity of objects
and so the the disembodied General
generalized uh General generative models
we lose sight of it because it's like it
feels like we can totally Define the
whole setting
therefore the parameters of the
generative model should be like
maximally interpretive
but that might not even be true for the
in silico case
so especially when we're taking the
metabasian perspective
from chapter nine
and we're thinking about doing inference
on an inference Doer
there's a lot of
you know X only makes sense of Y which
only makes sense in light of Z
and I think it's actually that more
complex
predicate I'm not sure if that's the
accurate way to say it
but it's the more
complex setup
in the metabasian model
that's one of the energy barriers to
understanding not just active
but just
good science
and the map territory
and all these other related topics
especially because this dashed line
that's our own Gray Zone
so our own parameterization is only
going to make sense in light of things
that we almost surely didn't specify
even our own parameterization about it
ourselves
and so like understanding I mean then to
kind of come all the way back
foreign
leads us to an existentialist like who
are we what are we where are we going
why are we doing that but
of course that's one of the
places that you'll get to
in this road network with a high road in
the low road
um
one area we didn't go too much into
which is totally understandable given
just
that it's a textbook that we've read
over the last several months and all
that is like the citations
and just okay you know structure
learning
Tenenbaum 2008 well we know Tenenbaum is
still
active
so and it's always useful to cite
earlier papers that are more positional
however
um
there's a lot of threads that could be
connected to like I don't know a 2019
review on structure learning techniques
so that the framing of the question and
the comparators might be a little bit
more modern
learning to learn in machine learning
formation of learning sets
the seriously brain damaged monkey
developed sets which allowed him to
behave more efficiently than the
untrained non-brain damaged monkey
it's brain damage is adaptive is that
what
this is the abstract that's not the
conclusion but
I just can't help it that's yeah
you can see that the clickbait headlines
already
me
um
I don't know continuing this the title
of the chapter and um
another question about categories from
the last uh session here like
what what
do what is is there a specific active
inference definition of sentient
how does that relate to
you know attention salience epistemic
Dynamics and not going down that
existential rabbit hole we just
left off on uh
doctor sentient
Ellie what's is there an active specific
uh I think he dropped off in a second
he's back but if you could talk Ali but
I I just I joke because I know Ali was
well
um
the upcoming Live guest stream that
we'll have
with the um authors
okay
so that they recently had this papers in
vitro neurons learned exhibit sentience
when embodied in a simulated Game World
they played pong
and and then like people were
um yeah okay people were freaking out
because it was just like a sentient as
conscious but Ali what is the take
well uh I'm I'm not exactly sure what uh
I mean what what was the controversy
about because uh it's it was merely
about just uh alexical meaning uh of a
term uh which is uh obviously something
that that you can look up in a
dictionary and get those lexical
meanings because uh the word sentient uh
is uh defined in Oxford English
Dictionary as uh an organism that
responds to stimuli that's it so one act
at least one of the meanings of the word
sentient so yeah I was not sure
why that the use of this word uh raise
the I mean so much controversy on
Twitter and around because that's
basically how this word was used even in
uh 19 and 18th century so uh I mean
before all these uh developments in
artificial intelligence and philosophy
of mind and so on so uh that's just
minimal requirement of to for something
to be described as sentient
yeah I I guess
um this framing
distinct Centier you know in Spanish
mesiento I feel a certain way
it's situated in a not just a
cognitivist but a phenomenological space
and so
I believe that's some of the baggage
people brought but you're totally right
going to another mainstream source
it simply is the responsivity
to Sensations
is that like exhibiting agency
I don't think exhibiting policy
selection you know
I don't even think it has to act
something could be sentient and not take
actions
although one could then could you could
say if it doesn't take internal actions
or covert actions of some kind
then was the impression made
or was it just you know Teflon just
sliding off of its perceptual apparatus
so
um but
I mean
it is what this chapter's title hinges
on
yeah it is
I'm not sure I'm not sure that we
I don't know uh
yeah it's it's still a little confusing
in the light in the context of active
inference to me I think like
it would have to be like the case that
you like you're saying you know some
sort of action was taken maybe it's a
hidden state or something you know from
the but uh
I don't see how yeah like
it could be responsive to stimuli
and not act like um
because I mean
I don't know like a rock rolling down a
hill is responding to the stimuli of the
you know gravitational geodesic there
it's like is that you know what I mean
like that's not really
um
that's not response to simulai right so
that's probably outside of the
definition there I don't know maybe in
Bayesian mechanics it's not but
does sentient even add anything
and are we only talking about organisms
organisms in the kantian definition is
the unit of biological organization that
is the end in and of itself
not that that necessarily helps whereas
a more modern replicator evolutionary
definition describes the organism as
like The evolutionary unit or replicator
um like the ant colony as an organism
um and then olly I just saw you linked
agential realism I mean could this have
just been one of the benefits of active
is it provides again we talked last week
whether it's complete
um provides a solution to the Adaptive
problems that agents have to solve
or inactive agents or active entities or
active inferors
have to solve
but not not sure whether this
brings in some lateral
associations and over specifications
that aren't necessarily entailed by
simply active inference
okay uh actually uh Karen Barat uh I
mean uh
the physicist to propose this
um ontological stance of agential
realism
defines agency
um as a kind of relationship between
objects and not exactly as something
that a subject or an organism has or
capacity of an organism or a cognitive
agent so to speak so in this sense if we
look at
um this definition of agency we can say
that every kind of organism and every
kind of even
persistent objects in various time
scales would necessarily have some kind
of agencies
what
agencies and other
polycamists were of course because it
can refer to the agent-like behavior
meaning something you'd specify more as
like a
mobile actor in a agent-based model but
also it is then used to specifically
also mean taking action
and like in the Bayesian physics
the textbook does not engage
deeply with Bayesian physics
and it will be interesting to see in the
coming
[Music]
one to three years
as um
Dalton's at all's work becomes
percolating through the space
and potentially as reflected by a second
textbook with friston and maybe others
at MIT press
um
whether
this the different specified kinds of
particles
help us
step outside of some of the previous
framings of agent and agency
so if agent is just going to mean thing
we have a way to talk about thankedness
in terms of its repeated measurements
Quantum things
thermodynamic things cognitive things so
we have a good thing definition
first in 2019 which is cited in this
textbook but it's not gone into too much
um
and then
we could talk about mode matching mode
tracking mode tracking and path tracking
things
and chaotic things and strange things
and so
um a piece of wood floating down the
river
is following a path of least action that
doesn't entail any cognitive model
it is a thing it's agentic
but it's not taking agency
if it were um
a stick
with um a different apparatus or
increasingly different kinds of policy
selection mechanisms
that wouldn't change its thingness but
it would be a different kind of thing
also I I um hope it's okay to share that
and anyone who's watching uh on Monday
at um 6 30 A.M
PT
Maxwell ramstead is going to be giving
um
meeting
at the theoretical neurobiology group so
email active inference if you want more
information
but he's going to be talking about some
of these areas
basically as part of
this
banner year of 2022.
um
I believe there are some
threads around
Ollie you can totally say it differently
if you if you see it differently but
like um
kind of standing with two feet in
octave and fep
as a framework in a filter as Dean might
say
rather than
this procrustian journey
of trying to stretch and distort what
fep is into other ontologies
that might have false positives
negatives
no quantitative definition in sight and
so on
and like just the way that so much ink
and attention has been spent on
framing fep Within
past lineages of debate
or trying to bring it to bear on one
side or the other
but I think that reflects a Time coming
when a true fep interpretation actually
is possible rather than seeing fep as
interpreted by others
but that will be kind of interesting
um
okay well we have five more minutes
oh
what a year
it seems like going faster
would have been challenging
one chapter per week would have been
a blitz
three chapters per week I mean I mean
three three weeks per chapter yeah
exactly
um three weeks per chapter would have
taken us
into the
um you know two-thirds of a year
range
with some
modifications and improvements that I
hope everybody will engage in and and
have so much to contribute to like in
future textbook groups and and other
affordances
this is something like
a semester-long course
and that
um like a four unit course or something
where for two weeks reading a chapter
with a few other selections
so providing some other work and maybe
starting slightly differently
maybe but these are all things that we
can explore just kind of like raising
them I know that all of you are thinking
about this too but just wanted to like
say it
um
within the context of a semester course
and initially more like a seminar course
like we're working through it
and some people like read and understand
highly all the material other people
like
um fight through and
get through some of it
but it all just is what it is
before becoming more of like
a graded course not even saying that
we're gonna grade I'm just saying like
there is a format archetype
where challenging material is addressed
usually as a graduate seminar
and you basically pass if you
participate
and it doesn't require tests at all
before we get into other kinds of
Assessments and everything
um
any thoughts in the last minutes here
uh thank you for doing this and
having the cognitive range to the answer
between
all these disparate
gestures that we throw at you and uh
yeah I really enjoyed it so
thank you and also just one last night I
maybe said it for some earlier but um
we're in contact with the authors and
with the publisher
and um like I sent them some updates
they're super excited
um so we could schedule time to all talk
potentially as like recorded but not
live streamed
um in early 23 with at least Thomas if
not others
and um we can return next week to some
of the the future steps and things like
that
but it's just like
it'll be cool
all right next week
all right thank you fellows farewell
bye thank you everyone bye